<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 id="id-errors">	
<head>Summary of Error Conditions</head>	
  

<p>This document uses the <code>err</code> prefix which represents the
same namespace URI (http://www.w3.org/2005/xqt-errors) as defined in
<bibref ref="xpath-31" diff="chg" at="2013-12-07"/>.  Use of this
namespace prefix binding in this document is not normative.</p>
<error-list>

<error code="0001" class="NR" type="serialization" spec="SE">
<p>It is an error if an item in <emph>S<sub>6</sub></emph> in <termref
def="sequence-normalization">sequence normalization</termref> is an
attribute node or a namespace node.</p></error>


<error spec="SE" code="0003" class="RE" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the <termref
def="serializer">serializer</termref> is unable to satisfy the rules
for either a well-formed XML document entity or a well-formed XML
external general parsed entity, or both, except for content modified
by the character expansion phase of serialization.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0004" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error to specify the doctype-system parameter, or to
specify the standalone parameter with a value other than
<code>omit</code>, if the instance of the data model contains text
nodes or multiple element nodes as children of the root
node.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0005" class="RE" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the serialized result would contain an
<xnt spec="Names" ref="NT-NCName">NCName</xnt> that contains a character that is not
permitted by the version of Namespaces in XML specified by the
<code>version</code> parameter.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0006" class="RE" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the serialized result would contain a character
that is not permitted by the version of XML specified by the
<code>version</code> parameter.</p>
</error>

<error spec="SE" code="0007" class="SU" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if an output encoding other than <code>UTF-8</code>
or <code>UTF-16</code> is requested and the <termref
def="serializer">serializer</termref> does not support that
encoding.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0008" class="RE" type="serialization">
<!--Should this be merged with 0015 into a more generic error?-->
<p>It is an error if a character that cannot be represented in the
encoding that the <termref def="serializer">serializer</termref> is
using for output appears in a context where character references are
not allowed (for example if the character occurs in the name of an
element).</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0009" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the <code>omit-xml-declaration</code> parameter
has the value <code>yes</code>, 
<phrase diff="add" at="2016-07-07"><code>true</code> or <code>1</code></phrase>,
and the <code>standalone</code>
attribute has a value other than <code>omit</code>; or the
<code>version</code> parameter has a value other than <code>1.0</code>
and the <code>doctype-system</code> parameter is
specified.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0010" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the output method is <code>xml</code> or
<code>xhtml</code>, the value of the <code>undeclare-prefixes</code>
parameter is 
<phrase diff="add" at="2016-07-07">one of</phrase>,
<code>yes</code>,
<phrase diff="add" at="2016-07-07"> <code>true</code> or <code>1</code></phrase>,
and the value of the
<code>version</code> parameter is 1.0.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0011" class="SU" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the value of the <code>normalization-form</code>
parameter specifies a normalization form that is not supported by the
<termref def="serializer">serializer</termref>.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0012" class="RE" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the value of the <code>normalization-form</code>
parameter is <code>fully-normalized</code> and any relevant construct
of the result begins with a combining character.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0013" class="SU" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if the <termref
def="serializer">serializer</termref> does not support the version of
XML or HTML specified by the <code>version</code> parameter.</p>
</error>

<error spec="SE" code="0014" class="RE" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error to use the HTML output method if characters which
are permitted in XML but not in HTML appear in the instance of the
data model.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0015" class="RE" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error to use the HTML output method when <code>&gt;</code>
appears within a processing instruction in the data model instance
being serialized.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0016" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if a parameter value is invalid for the defined
domain.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0017" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if evaluating an expression in order to extract the
setting of a serialization parameter from a data model instance would
yield an error.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0018" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if evaluating an expression in order to extract the
setting of the <code>use-character-maps</code> serialization parameter
from a data model instance would yield a sequence of length greater
than one.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0019" class="PM" type="serialization">
<p>It is an error if an instance of the data model used to specify the
settings of serialization parameters specifies the value of the same
parameter more than once.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0020" class="RE" type="serialization" 
diff="add" at="2014-09-22">
<p>It is an error if a numeric value being serialized using the 
JSON output method cannot be represented in the JSON grammar
(e.g. <code>+INF</code>, <code>-INF</code>, <code>NaN</code>).
</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0021" class="RE" type="serialization" 
diff="add" at="2014-09-22">
<p>It is an error if a sequence being serialized using the JSON output
method includes items for which no rules are provided in the
appropriate section of the serialization rules.</p></error>

<!--* I'm guessing that "RE" is the right class here; it seems to
cover errors in representing the XDM instance using the serialized
form *-->
<error spec="SE" code="0022" class="RE" type="serialization" 
diff="add" at="2014-09-22">
<p>It is an error if a map being serialized using the JSON output method
has two keys with the same string value, unless the 
<code>allow-duplicate-names</code> has the value
<code>yes</code>,
<phrase diff="add" at="2016-07-07"> <code>true</code> or <code>1</code></phrase>.</p></error>

<error spec="SE" code="0023" class="RE" type="serialization" 
diff="add" at="2014-11-06">
<p>It is an error if a sequence being serialized using the JSON output
method is of length greater than one.</p></error>

</error-list>
</div1>

