<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 id="id-errors">	
  <head>Error Conditions</head>	

<error-list>

<error spec="FT" code="0001" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that does not support the FTMildNot operator must raise 
a static error if a full-text query contains a mild not.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0002" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that enforces one of the restrictions on FTUnaryNot must
raise a static error if a full-text query does not obey the restriction.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0003" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that does not support one or more of the choices on FTUnit
and FTBigUnit must
raise a static error if a full-text query contains one of those choices.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0004" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that does not support the FTScope operator must raise
a static error if a full-text query contains a scope.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0005" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that does not support the FTTimes operator must raise
a static error if a full-text query contains a times.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0006" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that restricts the use of FTStopWordOption must raise
a static error if a full-text query contains a stop word option that does not
meet the restriction.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0007" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that restricts the use of FTIgnoreOption must raise
a static error if a full-text query contains an ignore option that does not
meet the restriction.</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0008" class="ST" type="static">
<p>It is a static error if, during the static analysis phase, the query is
found to contain a stop word option that refers to a stop word list that is not
found in the statically known stop word lists.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0009" class="ST" type="static">
<p>It may be a static error if, during the static analysis phase, the query is
found to contain a language identifier in a language option that the
implementation does not support. The implementation may choose not to raise
this error and instead provide some other implementation-defined behavior.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0010" class="ST" type="static">
<p>It is a static error if, during the static analysis phase,
an expression is found to use an FTOrder operator that does not appear
directly succeeding an FTWindow or an FTDistance operator and the
implementation enforces this restriction.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0011" class="ST" type="static">
<p>An implementation may restrict the use of FTWindow and FTDistance to an FTOr
that is either a single FTWords or a combination of FTWords involving
only the operators <phrase diff="chg">ftand and ftor</phrase>. 
If it a static error if, during the
static analysis phase, an expression is found that violates this restriction
and the implementation enforces this restriction.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0012" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
An implementation that does not support the FTContent operator must raise
a static error if a full-text query contains one.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0013" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
It is a static error if, during the static analysis phase, 
an implementation that restricts the use of FTLanguageOption to a single
language, encounters more than one distinct language option.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0014" class="ST" type="static">
<p>An implementation may constrain the form of the expression used to compute
scores. It is a static error if, during the static analysis phase, 
such an implementation encounters a scoring expression that does not meet
the restriction.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0015" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
It is a static error if, during the static analysis phase, 
an implementation that restricts the choices of FTCaseOption
encounters the "lowercase" or "uppercase" option.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0016" class="DY" type="dynamic">
<p>
It is a dynamic error if a weight value is not within the required range of values;
it is also a dynamic error if an implementation that does not support negative weights
encounters a negative weight value. 
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0017" class="DY" type="dynamic">
<p>
It is a dynamic error if an implementation encounters a mild not 
selection, one of whose operands evaluates to an &AllMatches; that contains a
&StringExclude; 
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0018" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
It is a static error if, during the static analysis phase, the query is found
to contain a thesaurus option that refers to a thesaurus that is not found in
the statically known thesauri.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0019" class="ST" type="static">
<p>
It is a static error if,
within a single <nt def="FTMatchOptions">FTMatchOptions</nt>,
there is more than one match option of any given 
<termref def="dt-match-option-group">match option group</termref>.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FT" code="0020" class="DY" type="dynamic">
<p>
It is a dynamic error if,
when "wildcards" is in effect,
a query string violates wildcard syntax.
</p>
</error>

<error spec="FO" code="0002" class="CH" type="dynamic">
<p>It is a dynamic error if, in a function invocation, the argument corresponding to
the specified function's collation parameter does not identify a supported collation.</p></error>

<error spec="XP" code="0003" class="ST" type="static">
<p>It is a static error if an expression is not a valid instance of the grammar defined in
<specref ref="id-grammar"/> or of the grammar defined in <specref ref="id-xpath-grammar"/>.</p></error>

<error spec="XP" code="0004" class="TY" type="type">
<p>It is a type error if, during the static analysis phase,
an expression is found to have a static type
that is not appropriate for the context in which the expression occurs, or during the
dynamic evaluation phase, the dynamic type of a value does not match a required type as
specified by the matching rules in <xspecref spec="XP" ref="id-sequencetype-matching"/>.</p></error>

<error spec="XQ" code="0013" class="ST" type="static">
<p>It is a static error if an implementation recognizes a pragma but determines that its content is invalid.</p></error>

<error spec="XQ" code="0079" class="ST" type="static">
<p>It is a static error if an extension expression contains neither
   a pragma that is recognized by the implementation nor
   an expression enclosed in curly braces.</p></error>

</error-list>

</div1>
