<div1 id="id-xqft-xqueryx">
<head>XML Syntax (XQueryX) for &language;</head>

<p>
<bibref ref="xqueryx"/> defines an XML representation of <bibref ref="xquery"/>. 
<bibref ref="xpath-full-text-10-requirements"/>, section 5.4, XML Syntax, states
"XQuery and XPath Full Text MAY have more than one syntax binding. 
One query language syntax MUST be expressed in XML in a way that
reflects the underlying structure of the query. See XML Query Requirements."
This appendix specifies XML Schemas that together define the
XML representation of &language; by representing the abstract syntax
found in <specref ref="id-grammar"/>.  Because &language;
integrates seamlessly with XQuery 1.0,
it follows that the XML Syntax for &language; must integrate well
with the XML Syntax for XQuery 1.0. 
</p>

<p>
The XML Schema specified in this appendix accomplishes integration by importing
the XML Schema defined for XQueryX in <xspecref spec="XQX" ref="Schema"/>,
incorporating all of its type and element definitions. 
It then extends that schema by adding definitions of new types and elements
in a namespace belonging to the full-text specification. 
</p>

<p>
The semantics of a Full Text XQueryX document are determined by the
semantics of the XQuery Full Text expression that
results from transforming the XQueryX document into XQuery Full Text
syntax using the XSLT stylesheet that appears in
section <specref ref="id-xqft-full-text-stylesheet"/>. 
The "correctness" of that transformation is determined by
asking the following the question:
Can some Full Text XQueryX processor QX process some
Full Text XQueryX document D1 to produce results R1,
after which the stylesheet is used to translate D1 into an
XQuery Full Text expression E1 that, when processed by some
XQuery Full Text processor Q, produces results R2 that are equivalent
(under some meaningful definition of "equivalent") to results R1?
</p>


<div2 id="id-xqft-full-text-schema">
<head>XQueryX representation of &language;</head>

<p>
The XML Schema that defines the complex types and elements
for XQueryX in support of &language;, including the ftContainsExpr,
incorporates a second XML Schema that defines
types and elements to support the ftMatchOption. 
Both XML Schemas are defined in this section. 
</p>

<eg>
&xqftxqx-schema;
</eg>

<eg>
&xqftxqx-options-schema;
</eg>

</div2>


<div2 id="id-xqft-full-text-stylesheet">
<head>XQueryX stylesheet for &language;</head>

<p>
The XSLT stylesheet that defines the semantics of XQueryX
in support of &language; integrates seamlessly with the
XQueryX XSLT stylesheet defined in <xspecref spec="XQX" ref="Stylesheet"/>
by importing the XQueryX XSLT stylesheet. 
It provides additional templates that
define the semantics of the XQueryX representation of &language;
by transforming that XQueryX representation into
the human readable syntax of &language;. 
</p>

<eg>
&xqftxqx-stylesheet;
</eg>

</div2>


<div2 id="id-xqft-full-text-examples">
<head>XQueryX for &language; example</head>

<!-- Jim, 2007-08-11 - Bug #4735 -->
<p>
The following example is based on the data and queries of one of the use cases
in <bibref ref="xpath-full-text-10-use-cases"/>. 
In this example, we show the English description of the query,
the XQuery Full Text solution given in <bibref ref="xpath-full-text-10-use-cases"/>,
a Full Text XQueryX solution, and the XQuery Full Text query
that results from applying the Full Text XQueryX-to-XQuery Full Text transformation
defined by the stylesheet in <specref ref="id-xqft-full-text-stylesheet"/>
to the Full Text XQueryX solution.
The latter XQuery Full Text expression is presented only as a sanity-check &mdash;
the intent of the stylesheet is not to create the identical
XQuery Full Text expression given in <bibref ref="xpath-full-text-10-use-cases"/>,
but to produce <emph>a</emph> valid
XQuery Full Text expression with the same semantics. 
</p>

<p>Comparison of the results of the Full Text XQueryX-to-XQuery Full Text
transformation given in this document with the XQuery Full Text solutions
in the <bibref ref="xpath-full-text-10-use-cases"/> may be helpful in evaluating
the correctness of the Full Text XQueryX solution in the example. </p>

<p>The XQuery Full Text Use Cases solution given for the
example is provided only to assist readers of this
document in understanding the Full Text XQueryX solution. 
There is no intent to imply that this
document specifies a "compilation" or "transformation" of
XQuery Full Text syntax into Full Text XQueryX syntax. 
</p>

<p>In the following example, note that path expressions are expanded to show their
structure. Also, note that the prefix syntax for binary operators like "and" makes the
precedence explicit. In general, humans find it easier to read an XML representation
that does not expand path expressions, but it is less convenient for programmatic
representation and manipulation.  XQueryX is designed as a language that is convenient
for production and modification by software, and not as a convenient syntax for humans to
read and write. </p>

<p>Finally, please note that white space, including new lines, have been added to
some of the Full Text XQueryX documents and XQuery Full Text expressions for readability. 
That additional white space is not necessarily produced by the
Full Text XQueryX-to-XQuery Full Text transformation. </p>

      <div3 id="Example1">
        <head>Example</head>

        <p>Here is Q4 from the <bibref ref="xpath-full-text-10-use-cases"/>,
    use case SCORE: Find all books with parts about "usability testing".</p>

        <div4 id="Example1-XQuery-Full-Text">
          <head>XQuery solution in XQuery and XPath Full Text 1.0 Use Cases:</head>

          <eg role="xquery">&ftxqxexmpl1xqft;</eg>

        </div4>

        <div4 id="Example1-Full-Text-XQueryX">
          <head>A Solution in Full Text XQueryX:</head>

          <eg>&ftxqxexmpl1ftxqx;</eg>

        </div4>

        <div4 id="Example1-Full-Text-Transformation">
          <head>Transformation of Full Text XQueryX Solution into XQuery Full Text</head>

          <p>Application of the stylesheet in <specref ref="id-xqft-full-text-stylesheet"/>
          to the Full Text XQueryX solution results in:</p>

          <eg role="xquery">&ftxqxexmpl1ftxqx2xqft;</eg>

        </div4>

    </div3>

</div2>

</div1>
