<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 id="id-conformance">
    <head>Conformance</head>

    <note role="xquery" diff="del" at="bug28782">
        <p>The XQuery Working Group has not yet determined conformance criteria for XQuery 3.1; in
            particular, we have not decided which of the new features of XQuery 3.1 are optional.
            This section currently contains the conformance criteria for XQuery 3.0, with two
            modifications: (1) support for all axes is now required, (2) conformance criteria for
            syntax extensions are given.</p>
    </note>

    <p>This section defines the conformance criteria for an &language; processor. In this section, the
        following terms are used to indicate the requirement levels defined in <bibref ref="RFC2119"
        />. <termdef id="must" term="must"><term>MUST</term> means that the item is an absolute
            requirement of the specification.</termdef>
        <termdef id="mustnot" term="must not"><term>MUST NOT</term> means that the item is an
            absolute prohibition of the specification.</termdef>
        <termdef id="may" term="may"><term>MAY</term> means that an item is truly
            optional.</termdef>
        <termdef id="should" term="should" role="xquery"><term>SHOULD</term> means that there may exist valid
            reasons in particular circumstances to ignore a particular item, but the full
            implications must be understood and carefully weighed before choosing a different
            course.</termdef>
    </p>


      <p role="xpath">XPath is intended primarily as a component that can be used by
      other specifications. Therefore, XPath relies on specifications that
      use it (such as <bibref ref="XPTR"/> and <bibref ref="xslt-30"/>) to
      specify conformance criteria for XPath in their respective
      environments. Specifications that set conformance criteria for their
      use of XPath <termref def="mustnot" diff="chg">MUST NOT</termref> change the
      syntactic or semantic definitions of XPath as given in this
      specification, except by subsetting and/or compatible extensions.</p>
      
      <p role="xpath"><phrase diff="add" at="bug29498">If a language is described as an extension of XPath, 
      then every expression that conforms to the XPath grammar <termref def="must">MUST</termref>  behave as described in this specification.</phrase>
      <phrase diff="del" at="bug29498">The specification of such a language may describe it as an
      extension of XPath provided that every expression that conforms to the
      XPath grammar behaves as described in this specification.</phrase></p>

      <p role="xquery">An XQuery processor that claims to conform to
      this specification <termref def="must" >MUST</termref> include a
      claim of Minimal Conformance as defined in <specref
      ref="id-minimal-conformance"/>. In addition to a claim of
      Minimal Conformance, it <termref def="may">MAY</termref> claim
      conformance to one or more optional features defined in <specref
      ref="id-conform-optional-features"/>.</p>

      <div2 id="id-xpath-static-typing" role="xpath">
        <head>Static Typing Feature</head>

        <p>
          <termdef id="dt-xpath-static-typing-feature" term="static typing feature" role="xpath">The <term>Static
        Typing Feature</term> is an optional feature of XPath that provides support for static semantics, and requires implementations to detect and report <termref def="dt-type-error">type errors</termref> during the <termref def="dt-static-analysis">static analysis phase</termref>.</termdef> Specifications that use XPath <termref def="may" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MAY</termref>  specify conformance criteria for use of the Static Typing Feature.</p>
        <p>If an implementation does not support the <termref def="dt-xpath-static-typing-feature">Static Typing Feature</termref>, but can
        nevertheless determine during the static analysis phase that
        <phrase role="xquery">a <nt def="QueryBody">QueryBody</nt></phrase><phrase role="xpath">an XPath expression</phrase>, if evaluated, would necessarily raise a <termref def="dt-dynamic-error">dynamic error</termref> or that an expression, if evaluated, would necessarily raise a <termref def="dt-type-error">type error</termref>, the implementation <termref def="may" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MAY</termref> raise that error during the static analysis phase. The choice
        of whether to raise such an error at analysis time is <termref def="dt-implementation-dependent">implementation dependent</termref>.</p>

      </div2>

    <div2 id="id-minimal-conformance" role="xquery">
        <head>Minimal Conformance</head>
        <p>An implementation that claims <term>Minimal Conformance</term> to this specification
                <termref def="must">MUST</termref> provide all of the following items:</p>
        <olist>
            <item>
                <p>An implementation of everything specified in this document except those features
                    specified in <specref ref="id-conform-optional-features"/> to be optional. If an
                    implementation does not provide a given optional feature, it <termref def="must"
                        >MUST</termref> implement any requirements specified in <specref
                        ref="id-conform-optional-features"/> for implementations that do not provide
                    that feature.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>A definition of every item specified to be <termref
                        def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>, unless
                    that item is part of an optional feature that is not provided by the
                    implementation. A list of <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"
                        >implementation-defined</termref> items can be found in <specref
                        ref="id-impl-defined-items"/>.</p>
                <note>
                    <p>Implementations are not required to define items specified to be <termref
                            def="dt-implementation-dependent"
                        >implementation-dependent</termref>.</p>
                </note>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>An implementation of <bibref ref="xpath-datamodel-31"/>, as specified in <specref
                        ref="id-data-model-conformance"/>, and a definition of every item specified
                    to be <termref def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>,
                    unless that item is part of an optional feature that is not provided by the
                    implementation.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>An implementation of all functions defined in <bibref ref="xpath-functions-31"/>,
                    and a definition of every item specified to be <termref
                        def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>, unless
                    that function or item is part of an optional feature that is not provided by the
                    implementation.</p>
            </item>
        </olist>
    </div2>
    <div2 id="id-conform-optional-features" role="xquery">
        <head>Optional Features</head>

        <p>The features discussed in this section are optional. An implementation <termref def="may"
                >MAY</termref> claim conformance to one or more of these features.</p>

        <p>The description of each feature mentions any errors that <phrase diff="del" at="bug29498">may</phrase> occur if a query relies on a
            feature that is not present.</p>


        <div3 id="id-schema-aware-feature">
            <head>Schema Aware Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-schema-aware-feature" term="schema aware feature"
                    >The <term>Schema Aware Feature</term> permits the query Prolog to contain a
                        <termref def="dt-schema-import">schema import</termref>, and permits a query
                    to contain a <code>validate</code> expression (see <specref ref="id-validate"
                    />). </termdef>
            </p>

            <p>If an XQuery implementation does not provide the Schema Aware Feature, it <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> raise a static error <errorref class="ST" code="0009"
                /> if it encounters a schema import, and it <termref def="must">MUST</termref> raise
                a static error <errorref class="ST" code="0075"/> if it encounters a
                    <code>validate</code> expression.</p>

            <p>If an implementation provides the Schema Aware Feature, it <termref def="must"
                    >MUST</termref> also provide the <specref ref="id-typed-data-feature"/>.</p>
        </div3>


        <div3 id="id-typed-data-feature">
            <head>Typed Data Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-typed-data-feature" term="typed data feature">The
                        <term>Typed Data Feature</term> permits an XDM instance to contain element
                    node types other than <code>xs:untyped</code> and attributes node types other
                    than <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>.</termdef>
            </p>

            <p>If an XQuery implementation does not provide the Typed Data Feature, it <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> guarantee that:</p>

            <olist>
                <item>
                    <p>The XDM has the type <code>xs:untyped</code> for every element node and
                            <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code> for every attribute node, including nodes
                        created by the query.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Elements constructed by the query always have the type
                            <code>xs:untyped</code>; attributes constructed by the query always have
                        the type <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>. (This is equivalent to using
                            <code>construction mode = strip</code>.)</p>
                </item>
            </olist>
        </div3>

        <div3 id="id-static-typing-feature">
            <head>Static Typing Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-static-typing-feature" term="static
		  typing feature"
                    role="xquery">The <term>Static Typing Feature</term> requires implementations to
                    report all <termref def="dt-type-error">type errors</termref> during the
                        <termref def="dt-static-analysis">static analysis phase</termref>.</termdef>
            </p>


            <p>If an implementation provides the <termref def="dt-static-typing-feature">Static
                    Typing Feature</termref>, then it <termref def="must">MUST</termref> raise an
                error during static analysis whenever the inferred static type of an expression is
                not subsumed by the required type for the context in which it appears.</p>

            <p>If an implementation does not provide the <termref def="dt-static-typing-feature"
                    >Static Typing Feature</termref>, then it <termref diff="del" at ="bug28966" def="may">MAY</termref><termref diff="add" at ="bug28966" def="mustnot">MUST NOT</termref>
                report type errors during the static analysis phase <phrase diff="del" at ="bug28966">only</phrase><phrase diff="add" at ="bug28966">except</phrase> in cases where the inferred
                static type and the required type have an empty intersection (that is, where
                evaluation of the expression is guaranteed to fail). It <termref def="may">MAY</termref> defer some or all type checking until the dynamic evaluation
                phase.</p>
        </div3>
        <div3 id="id-module-feature">
            <head>Module Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-module-feature" term="module feature">The <term>Module
                        Feature</term> allows a query Prolog to contain a <term>Module Import</term>
                    and allows <term>library modules</term> to be created.</termdef>
            </p>
            <p>An implementation that does not provide the Module Feature <termref def="must"
                    >MUST</termref> raise a <termref def="dt-static-error">static error</termref>
                <errorref class="ST" code="0016"/> if it encounters a <termref
                    def="dt-module-declaration">module declaration</termref> or a <termref
                    def="dt-module-import">module import</termref>. Since a <termref
                    def="dt-module-declaration">module declaration</termref> is required in a
                    <termref def="dt-library-module">library module</termref>, the Module Feature is
                required in order to create a <termref def="dt-library-module">library module</termref>. </p>
            <note>
                <p>In the absence of the Module Feature, each query consists of a single <termref
                        def="dt-main-module">main module</termref>.</p>
            </note>
        </div3>
        <div3 id="id-serialization-feature">
            <head>Serialization Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-serialization-feature" term="serialization feature">The
                        <term>Serialization Feature</term> provides means for serializing the result
                    of a query as specified in <specref ref="id-serialization"/>.</termdef> A
                conforming XQuery implementation that provides the Serialization Feature <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> conform to <specref ref="id-serialization"/>. An
                implementation <termref def="may">MAY</termref> provide other forms of
                serialization, which do not conform to the Serialization Feature, and are beyond the
                scope of this specification. </p>
            <p>The means by which serialization is invoked is <termref
                    def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>.</p>
            <p>If an error is raised during the serialization process as specified in <bibref
                    ref="xslt-xquery-serialization-31"/>, an implementation <termref def="must"
                    >MUST</termref> report the error to the calling environment.</p>

            <p>An implementation that does not provide the Serialization Feature <termref def="must"
                    >MUST NOT</termref> raise errors when reading an <termref
                    def="dt-output-declaration">output declaration</termref>, and <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> implement <code>fn:serialize</code>; it <termref
                    def="may">MAY</termref>, however, raise an error when <code>fn:serialize</code>
                is invoked, as specified in <xspecref spec="FO31" ref="func-serialize"/>. An
                implementation that does not provide the Serialization Feature <termref def="may"
                    >MAY</termref> provide results of a query using a vendor-defined
                serialization.</p>

            <note>
                <p>Some implementations return query results without serialization. For instance, an
                    implementation might provide results via an XML API or a binary representation
                    such as a persistent DOM.</p>
            </note>
        </div3>

        <div3 id="id-higher-order-function-feature">
            <head>Higher-Order Function Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-higher-order-function-feature" term="higher-order function feature"
                    >The <term>Higher Order Function Feature</term> allows an expression to evaluate
                    to a function <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28810">item other than a map or array.</phrase></termdef>
            </p>

            <p>An implementation that does not provide the Higher-Order Function Feature <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> raise a static error <errorref class="ST" code="0129"
                /> if it encounters a <phrase diff="del" at="bug28810"><nt def="FunctionTest">FunctionTest</nt>, <termref
                    def="dt-dynamic-function-invocation">dynamic function call</termref>,</phrase> 
                    <phrase diff="add" at="bug28810"><nt def="TypedFunctionTest">TypedFunctionTest</nt>,</phrase> <termref
                    def="dt-named-function-ref">named function reference</termref>, <termref
                    def="dt-inline-func">inline function expression</termref>, or <termref
                    def="dt-partial-function-application">partial function application</termref>.  <phrase diff="add" at="bug28810">
                    The effect of this rule is that it is impossible to construct function items other than maps and arrays.
                    Dynamic function calls are permitted, but the function that is called will necessarily be a map or array.
                    The <nt def="AnyFunctionTest">AnyFunctionTest</nt> <termref def="dt-sequence-type">sequence type</termref> is permitted and will match either a map 
                    or array.</phrase>
                Such an implementation <termref def="may">MAY</termref> raise a type error <errorref
                    class="TY" code="0004"/> if an expression evaluates to a sequence that contains
                a function.</p>

            <p><phrase diff="chg" at="bug28810">If an implementation provides the Higher-Order Function Feature, then it <termref def="must" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MUST</termref> provide
                    all <xtermref spec="FO31" ref="dt-higher-order"/> functions defined in <bibref ref="xpath-functions-31"/>.</phrase>
                If an implementation does not provide the Higher
                Order Function Feature, a <termref def="dt-static-error">static error</termref> is
                raised <errorref class="ST" code="0017"/> if any of these functions is present in a
                query. </p>

        </div3>

        <div3 diff="del" at="bug 29959" id="id-fnput-feature">
            <head><code>fn:put()</code> Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-fnput-feature" term="fn:put()
                feature" >The <term>fn:put() Feature</term> allows the
                <code>fn:put()</code> function, defined in <bibref
                ref="xquery-update-30"/> , to be used in a
                query.</termdef>

                This feature is defined as an update because
                <code>fn:put()</code> has side effects. It is provided
                as a separate feature because some implementations <phrase diff="del" at="bug29498">may want</phrase>
                need to be able to output files even if they do not
                conform to the XQuery Update Facility specification.
            </p>

            <p>An implementation that does not provide the
            <term>fn:put() feature</term> <termref
            def="must">MUST</termref> raise an error <errorref
            class="ST" code="0017"/> if <code>fn:put()</code> is
            present in a query.</p>

            <p>An implementation that provides the
            <term>fn:put() feature</term> <termref
            def="must">MUST</termref> implement the function as
            defined in <bibref ref="xquery-update-30"/>.</p>

        </div3>

    </div2>
    <div2 id="id-data-model-conformance" role="xquery">
        <head>Data Model Conformance</head>
        <p>All XQuery implementations process data represented in the <termref def="dt-datamodel"
                >data model</termref> as specified in <bibref ref="xpath-datamodel-31"/>. The data
            model specification relies on languages such as XQuery to specify conformance criteria
            for the data model in their respective environments, and suggests that the following
            issues should be considered:</p>
        <olist>
            <item>
                <p>
                    <emph>Support for normative construction from an infoset.</emph> An
                    implementation <termref def="may">MAY</termref> choose to claim conformance to
                        <xspecref spec="DM31" ref="const-infoset"/>, which defines a normative way
                    to construct an <termref def="dt-data-model-instance">XDM instance</termref>
                    from an XML document that is merely well-formed or is governed by a DTD.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>
                    <emph>Support for normative construction from a PSVI.</emph> An implementation
                        <termref def="may">MAY</termref> choose to claim conformance to <xspecref
                        spec="DM31" ref="const-psvi"/>, which defines a normative way to construct
                    an <termref def="dt-data-model-instance">XDM instance</termref> from an XML
                    document that is governed by a W3C XML Schema.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>
                    <emph>Support for versions of XML and XSD.</emph> As stated in <bibref
                        ref="xpath-datamodel-31"/>, <phrase diff="del" at="bug29498">it is recommended (but not required) that</phrase> the
                    definitions of primitives such as strings, characters, and names <termref def="should" diff="chg" at="bug29498">SHOULD</termref> be taken
                    from the latest applicable version of the base specifications in which they are
                    defined; it is implementation-defined which definitions are used in cases where
                    these differ. </p>
                <note>
                    <p>For suggestions on processing XML 1.1 documents with XSD 1.0, see <bibref
                            ref="xml11schema10"/>.</p>
                </note>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p><emph>Ranges of data values.</emph> In XQuery, the following limits are <termref
                        def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>:</p>
                <olist>
                    <item>
                        <p>For the <code>xs:decimal</code> type, the maximum number of decimal
                            digits (<code>totalDigits</code> facet) <termref def="must" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MUST</termref> be at least 18.
                            <phrase diff="add" at="bug29419">This limit <termref def="should">SHOULD</termref> be at least 20 digits in order to accommodate the full range of values of built-in subtypes of <code>xs:integer</code>, such as <code>xs:long</code> and <code>xs:unsignedLong</code>.</phrase>
                        </p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p diff="del" at="bug29576">For the types <code>xs:date</code>, <code>xs:time</code>,
                                <code>xs:dateTime</code>, <code>xs:gYear</code>, and
                                <code>xs:gYearMonth</code>: the maximum value of the year component
                            and the maximum number of fractional second digits (<termref def="must" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MUST</termref> be at least
                            3).</p>

                        <p diff="add" at="bug29576">For the types <code>xs:date</code>, <code>xs:dateTime</code>, <code>xs:gYear</code>, and <code>xs:gYearMonth</code>: the minimum and maximum value of the year component (must be at least 1 to 9999).</p>

                        <p diff="add" at="bug29576">For the types <code>xs:time</code> and <code>xs:dateTime</code>: the maximum number of fractional second digits (must be at least 3).</p>

                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>For the <code>xs:duration type</code>: the maximum absolute values of the
                            years, months, days, hours, minutes, and seconds components.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>For the <code>xs:yearMonthDuration</code> type: the maximum absolute
                            value, expressed as an integer number of months.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>For the <code>xs:dayTimeDuration</code> type: the maximum absolute value,
                            expressed as a decimal number of seconds.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>For the types <code>xs:string</code>, <code>xs:hexBinary</code>,
                                <code>xs:base64Binary</code>, <code>xs:QName</code>,
                                <code>xs:anyURI</code>, <code>xs:NOTATION</code>, and types derived
                            from them: limitations (if any) imposed by the implementation on lengths
                            of values.</p>
                    </item>
                </olist>
                <p>The limits listed above need not be fixed, but <termref def="may" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MAY</termref>  depend on environmental
                    factors such as system resources. For example, the length of a value of type
                        <code>xs:string</code> <phrase diff="chg" at="bug29498">might</phrase> be limited by available memory.</p>
                <note>
                    <p>For discussion of errors due to <termref def="dt-implementation-dependent"
                            >implementation-dependent</termref> limits, see <specref
                            ref="id-kinds-of-errors"/>.</p>
                </note>
            </item>
        </olist>
    </div2>
    <div2 id="id-syntax-extensions" role="xquery">
        <head>Syntax Extensions</head>
        <p>Any syntactic extensions to XQuery are <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"
                >implementation-defined</termref>. The effect of syntactic extensions, including
            their error behavior, is <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"
                >implementation-defined</termref>. Syntactic extensions <termref def="may" diff="chg" at="bug29498">MAY</termref> be used without
            restriction to modify the semantics of a XQuery expression.</p>

    </div2>
</div1>
