<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<div1 role="xquery" id="id-mime-type">

  <head>The <code>application/xquery</code> Media Type</head>



  <p>This Appendix 

    specifies the media type for XQuery Version 1.0.  XQuery is a language for querying over

    collections of data from XML data sources, as specified in the main body of this document. This media type is being 

submitted to the IESG (Internet Engineering Steering Group)

for review, approval, and registration with IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers

Authority.)</p>



  <div2 id="id-mime-type-intro">

    <head>Introduction</head>

    <p>

	This document, found at

	<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/" role="xquery">http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/</loc>,

	together with its normative references,  defines the language XQuery Version 1.0.  This Appendix

      provides information about the <code>application/xquery</code> media type,

      which is intended to be used for transmitting queries written in the

      XQuery language.</p>

    <p>This document was prepared by members of the W3C XML Query Working

      Group.  Please send comments to public-qt-comments@w3.org,

      a public mailing list with archives at

      <loc href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-qt-comments">http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-qt-comments</loc>.</p></div2>



  <div2 id="id-registration-of-mime-type">

    <head>Registration of MIME Media Type <code>application/xquery</code></head>



    <p>MIME media type name:  <code>application</code></p>

    <p>MIME subtype name:    <code>xquery</code></p>

    <p>Required parameters:  none</p>

    <p>Optional parameters: none</p>

    <p>The syntax of XQuery is expressed in Unicode but may be written

	with any Unicode-compatible character encoding, including UTF-8 or

	UTF-16, or transported as US-ASCII or ISO-8859-1 with Unicode

	characters outside the range of the given encoding represented using

	an XML-style <code>&amp;#xddd;</code> syntax.</p>



      



      <div3 id="id-interoperability-considerations"><head>Interoperability Considerations</head>

	<p>None known.</p></div3>



      <div3 id="id-applications-of-media-type"><head>Applications Using this Media Type</head>

	<p>The public

	  <loc href="http://www.w3.org/XML/Query/">XQuery Web page</loc>

	  lists more than two dozen implementations of the XQuery language,

	  both proprietary and open source.</p>



	<p>This <phrase diff="del" at="2014-12-05">new</phrase> media
	type is <phrase diff="del" at="2014-12-05">being</phrase>
	registered to allow for deployment of XQuery on the World Wide
	Web.</p></div3>



      <div3 id="id-file-extensions"><head>File Extensions</head>

	<p>The most common file extensions in use for XQuery are

	  <code>.xq</code> and <code>.xquery</code>.</p>



	<p>The appropriate Macintosh file type code is <code>TEXT</code>.</p>

      </div3>



      



    <div3 id="id-intended-usage"><head>Intended Usage</head>

      <p>The intended usage of this media type is for interchange

	of XQuery expressions.</p></div3>



    <div3 id="id-author-change-controller"><head>Author/Change Controller</head>

      <p>XQuery was produced by, and is maintained by, the World Wide Web

	Consortium's XML Query Working Group.  The W3C has change

	control over this specification.</p></div3></div2>



  <div2 id="xquery-mime-encoding"><head>Encoding Considerations</head>



    <p>For use with transports that are not 8-bit clean, quoted-printable

    encoding is recommended since the XQuery syntax itself uses the

    US-ASCII-compatible subset of Unicode.</p>



  <p>An XQuery document may contain an <termref def="dt-encoding-declaration">encoding 

declaration</termref> as part of its <termref def="dt-version-declaration">version declaration</termref>:</p>

  <eg role="frag-prolog-parse-test">xquery version "3.1" encoding "utf-8";</eg>



  </div2>



<div2 id="xquery-mime-recognizing">

  <head>Recognizing XQuery Files</head>



  <p>An XQuery file may have the string <code>xquery version "V.V"</code> near the

    beginning of the document, where <code>"V.V"</code> is a version number.

    Currently the version number, if present, must be <code>"1.0"</code><phrase diff="add" at="2014-12-05">, <code>"3.0"</code>, or <code>"3.1"</code></phrase>.</p></div2>



<div2 id="id-charset-default-rules"><head>Charset Default Rules</head>



  <p>XQuery documents use the Unicode character set and, by default, the UTF-8 encoding.</p></div2>



<div2 id="id-security-considerations"><head>Security Considerations</head>



  <p>Queries written in XQuery may cause arbitrary URIs or IRIs to be

    dereferenced.  Therefore, the security issues of <bibref ref="RFC3987"/> Section 8 should be considered.

    In addition, the contents of resources identified by  <code>file:</code> URIs can in some cases be

    accessed, processed and returned as results. XQuery expressions can invoke any of the functions defined in

<bibref ref="xpath-functions-31"/>. For example, the

<code>fn:doc()</code> and <code>fn:doc-available()</code> functions  allow local filesystem probes as well as

access to any URI-defined resource accessible from the system

evaluating the XQuery expression.

<phrase diff="add" at="bug 30027">
The <code>fn:transform()</code> function allows calls to URI-identified
XSLT transformations which may in turn call external extension functions
and access or write to the file system. The <code>fn:transform()</code> function
should be sandboxed or disabled if untrusted queries are run.
</phrase>

</p><p>XQuery is a full declarative programming language, and supports

user-defined functions, external function libraries (modules)

referenced by URI, and system-specific "native" functions.</p><p>Arbitrary recursion is possible, as is arbitrarily large

memory usage, and implementations may place limits on CPU

and memory usage, as well as restricting access to system-defined

functions.

</p>



  <p diff="del" at="2014-12-05">The XML Query Working group is working on a facility to

    allow XQuery expressions to create and update 

    persistent data.  Untrusted queries should not be given write

    access to data.</p>

    <p diff="add" at="2014-12-05">
      The optional XQuery Update Facility allows XQuery expressions to
      create and update persistent data, potentially including writing
      to arbitrary locations on the local filesystem as well as to
      remote URIs. Untrusted queries should not be given write access
      to data.
    </p>


    <p>Furthermore, because the XQuery language permits extensions, 

    it is possible that <code>application/xquery</code>

    may describe content that has

    security implications beyond those described here.</p>

  </div2>

  </div1>
