<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<inform-div1 role="xquery" id="id-example-applications">
	<head>Example Applications</head>

	<p>This section contains examples of several important classes of queries that can be expressed
		using XQuery. The applications described here include joins across multiple data sources,
		grouping and aggregation, queries based on sequential relationships, recursive
		transformations, and selection of distinct combinations of values.</p>

	<note>
		<p diff="chg" at="bug28782">The new features of XQuery 3.0 and XQuery 3.1 can significantly simplify some of these queries.</p>
	</note>


	<div2 id="id-joins">
		<head>Joins</head>
		<p>Joins, which combine data from multiple sources into a single result, are a very
			important type of query. In this section we will illustrate how several types of joins
			can be expressed in XQuery. We will base our examples on the following three
			documents:</p>
		<olist>
			<item>
				<p>A document named <code>parts.xml</code> that contains many <code>part</code>
					elements; each <code>part</code> element in turn contains <code>partno</code>
					and <code>description</code> subelements.</p>
			</item>
			<item>
				<p>A document named <code>suppliers.xml</code> that contains many
						<code>supplier</code> elements; each <code>supplier</code> element in turn
					contains <code>suppno</code> and <code>suppname</code> subelements.</p>
			</item>
			<item>
				<p>A document named <code>catalog.xml</code> that contains information about the
					relationships between suppliers and parts. The catalog document contains many
						<code>item</code> elements, each of which in turn contains
						<code>partno</code>, <code>suppno</code>, and <code>price</code>
					subelements.</p>
			</item>
		</olist>
		<p>A conventional ("inner") join returns information from two or more related sources, as
			illustrated by the following example, which combines information from three documents.
			The example generates a "descriptive catalog" derived from the catalog document, but
			containing part descriptions instead of part numbers and supplier names instead of
			supplier numbers. The new catalog is ordered alphabetically by part description and
			secondarily by supplier name.</p>
		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[<descriptive-catalog>
   { 
     for $i in fn:doc("catalog.xml")/items/item,
         $p in fn:doc("parts.xml")/parts/part[partno = $i/partno],
         $s in fn:doc("suppliers.xml")/suppliers
                  /supplier[suppno = $i/suppno]
     order by $p/description, $s/suppname
     return
        <item>
           {
           $p/description,
           $s/suppname,
           $i/price
           }
        </item>
   }
</descriptive-catalog>]]></eg>
		<p>The previous query returns information only about parts that have suppliers and suppliers
			that have parts. An <term>outer join</term> is a join that preserves information from
			one or more of the participating sources, including elements that have no matching
			element in the other source. For example, a <term>left outer join</term> between
			suppliers and parts might return information about suppliers that have no matching
			parts. </p>
		<p>The following query demonstrates a left outer join. It returns names of all the suppliers
			in alphabetic order, including those that supply no parts. In the result, each supplier
			element contains the descriptions of all the parts it supplies, in alphabetic order.</p>
		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[for $s in fn:doc("suppliers.xml")/suppliers/supplier
order by $s/suppname
return
   <supplier>
      { 
        $s/suppname,
        for $i in fn:doc("catalog.xml")/items/item
                 [suppno = $s/suppno],
            $p in fn:doc("parts.xml")/parts/part
                 [partno = $i/partno]
        order by $p/description
        return $p/description 
      }
   </supplier>]]></eg>

		<p>The previous query preserves information about suppliers that supply no parts. Another
			type of join, called a <term>full outer join</term>, might be used to preserve
			information about both suppliers that supply no parts and parts that have no supplier.
			The result of a full outer join can be structured in any of several ways. The following
			query generates a list of <code>supplier</code> elements, each containing nested
				<code>part</code> elements for the parts that it supplies (if any), followed by a
			list of <code>part</code> elements for the parts that have no supplier. This might be
			thought of as a "supplier-centered" full outer join. Other forms of outer join queries
			are also possible.</p>

		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[<master-list>
 {
    for $s in fn:doc("suppliers.xml")/suppliers/supplier
    order by $s/suppname
    return
        <supplier>
           { 
             $s/suppname,
             for $i in fn:doc("catalog.xml")/items/item
                     [suppno = $s/suppno],
                 $p in fn:doc("parts.xml")/parts/part
                     [partno = $i/partno]
             order by $p/description
             return
                <part>
                   {
                     $p/description,
                     $i/price
                   }
                </part> 
           }
        </supplier> 
    ,
    (: parts that have no supplier :)
    <orphan-parts>
       { for $p in fn:doc("parts.xml")/parts/part
         where fn:empty(fn:doc("catalog.xml")/items/item
               [partno = $p/partno] )
         order by $p/description
         return $p/description 
       }
    </orphan-parts>
 }
</master-list>]]></eg>

		<p>The previous query uses an element constructor to enclose its output inside a
				<code>master-list</code> element. The concatenation operator (",") is used to
			combine the two main parts of the query. The result is an ordered sequence of
				<code>supplier</code> elements followed by an <code>orphan-parts</code> element that
			contains descriptions of all the parts that have no supplier.</p>
	</div2>

	<div2 id="id-queries-on-sequence">
		<head>Queries on Sequence</head>
		<p>XQuery uses the <code>&lt;&lt;</code> and <code>&gt;&gt;</code> operators to compare
			nodes based on document order. Although these operators are quite simple, they can be
			used to express complex queries for XML documents in which sequence is meaningful. The
			first two queries in this section involve a surgical report that contains
				<code>procedure</code>, <code>incision</code>, <code>instrument</code>,
				<code>action</code>, and <code>anesthesia</code> elements.</p>
		<p>The following query returns all the <code>action</code> elements that occur between the
			first and second <code>incision</code> elements inside the first procedure. The original
			document order among these nodes is preserved in the result of the query.</p>
		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[let $proc := /report/procedure[1]
for $i in $proc//action
where $i >> ($proc//incision)[1]
   and $i << ($proc//incision)[2]
return $i]]></eg>

		<p>It is worth noting here that document order is defined in such a way that a node is
			considered to precede its descendants in document order. In the surgical report, an
				<code>action</code> is never part of an <code>incision</code>, but an
				<code>instrument</code> is. Since the <code>&gt;&gt;</code> operator is based on
			document order, the predicate <code>$i &gt;&gt; ($proc//incision)[1]</code> is true for
			any <code>instrument</code> element that is a descendant of the first
				<code>incision</code> element in the first procedure.</p>
		<p>For some queries, it may be helpful to declare a function that can test whether a node
			precedes another node without being its ancestor. The following function returns
				<code>true</code> if its first operand precedes its second operand but is not an
			ancestor of its second operand; otherwise it returns <code>false</code>:</p>

		<eg role="frag-prolog-parse-test"><![CDATA[declare function local:precedes($a as node(), $b as node()) 
   as boolean
   {
      $a << $b
        and
      fn:empty($a//node() intersect $b) 
   };
]]></eg>


		<p>Similarly, a <code>local:follows</code> function could be written:</p>

		<eg role="frag-prolog-parse-test"><![CDATA[declare function local:follows($a as node(), $b as node()) 
   as boolean
   {
      $a >> $b
        and
      fn:empty($b//node() intersect $a) 
   };
]]></eg>

		<p>Using the <code>local:precedes</code> function, we can write a query that finds
				<code>instrument</code> elements between the first two incisions, excluding from the
			query result any <code>instrument</code> that is a descendant of the first
				<code>incision</code>:</p>

		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[let $proc := /report/procedure[1]
for $i in $proc//instrument
where local:precedes(($proc//incision)[1], $i)
   and local:precedes($i, ($proc//incision)[2])
return $i]]></eg>

		<p>The following query reports incisions for which no prior anesthesia was recorded in the
			surgical report. Since an <code>anesthesia</code> is never part of an
				<code>incision</code>, we can use <code>&lt;&lt;</code> instead of the
			less-efficient <code>local:precedes</code> function:</p>

		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[for $proc in /report/procedure
where some $i in $proc//incision satisfies
         fn:empty($proc//anesthesia[. << $i])
return $proc]]></eg>
		<p>In some documents, particular sequences of elements may indicate a logical hierarchy.
			This is most commonly true of HTML. The following query returns the introduction of an
			XHTML document, wrapping it in a <code>div</code> element. In this example, we assume
			that an <code>h2</code> element containing the text "Introduction" marks the beginning
			of the introduction, and the introduction continues until the next <code>h2</code> or
				<code>h1</code> element, or the end of the document, whichever comes first. </p>
		<eg role="parse-test"><![CDATA[let $intro := //h2[text()="Introduction"],
    $next-h := //(h1|h2)[. >> $intro][1]
return
   <div>
     {
       $intro,
       if (fn:empty($next-h))
         then //node()[. >> $intro]
         else //node()[. >> $intro and . << $next-h]
     }
   </div>]]></eg>
		<p>Note that the above query makes explicit the hierarchy that was implicit in the original
			document. In this example, we assume that the <code>h2</code> element containing the
			text "Introduction" has no subelements.</p>
	</div2>
	<div2 id="id-recursive-transformations">
		<head>Recursive Transformations</head>
		<p>Occasionally it is necessary to scan over a hierarchy of elements, applying some
			transformation at each level of the hierarchy. In XQuery this can be accomplished by
			defining a recursive function. In this section we will present two examples of such
			recursive functions.</p>
		<p>Suppose that we need to compute a table of contents for a given document by scanning over
			the document, retaining only elements named <code>section</code> or <code>title</code>,
			and preserving the hierarchical relationships among these elements. For each
				<code>section</code>, we retain subelements named <code>section</code> or
				<code>title</code>; but for each <code>title</code>, we retain the full content of
			the element. This might be accomplished by the following recursive function:</p>
		<eg role="frag-prolog-parse-test">
declare function local:sections-and-titles($n as node()) as node()? { 
   if (fn:local-name($n) = "section") then 
      element { fn:local-name($n) } { 
         for $c in $n/* 
         return local:sections-and-titles($c) 
      } 
   else if (fn:local-name($n) = "title") then 
      $n 
   else ( ) 
};</eg>
		<p>The "skeleton" of a given document, containing only its sections and titles, can then be
			obtained by invoking the <code>local:sections-and-titles</code> function on the root
			node of the document, as follows:</p>
		<eg role="parse-test">local:sections-and-titles(fn:doc("cookbook.xml"))</eg>
		<p>As another example of a recursive transformation, suppose that we wish to scan over a
			document, transforming every attribute named <code>color</code> to an element named
				<code>color</code>, and every element named <code>size</code> to an attribute named
				<code>size</code>. This can be accomplished by the following recursive function
			(note that the element constructor in case <code>$e</code> generates attributes before
			child elements):</p>
		<eg role="frag-prolog-parse-test">
declare function local:swizzle($n as node()) as node() {
   typeswitch($n) 
   case $a as attribute(color) 
      return element color { fn:string($a) } 
   case $es as element(size) 
      return attribute size { fn:string($es) } 
   case $e as element() 
      return element 
         { fn:local-name($e) } 
         { for $c in 
            ($e/@* except $e/@color,    (: attr -&gt; attr :) 
             $e/size,                   (: elem -&gt; attr :) 
             $e/@color,                 (: attr -&gt; elem :) 
             $e/node() except $e/size ) (: elem -&gt; elem :) 
           return local:swizzle($c) } 
   case $d as document-node() 
      return document 
         { for $c in $d/* return local:swizzle($c) } 
   default return $n 
};</eg>
		<p>The transformation can be applied to a whole document by invoking the
				<code>local:swizzle</code> function on the root node of the document, as
			follows:</p>
		<eg role="parse-test">local:swizzle(fn:doc("plans.xml"))</eg>
	</div2>
	<div2 id="id-select-distinct">
		<head>Selecting Distinct Combinations</head>
		<p>It is sometimes necessary to search through a set of data to find all the distinct
			combinations of a given list of properties. For example, an input data set might consist
			of a large set of <code>order</code> elements, each of which has the same basic
			structure, as illustrated by the following example:</p>
		<eg>&lt;order&gt; 
   &lt;date&gt;2003-10-15&lt;/date&gt; 
   &lt;product&gt;Dress Shirt&lt;/product&gt; 
   &lt;size&gt;M&lt;/size&gt; 
   &lt;color&gt;Blue&lt;/color&gt;
   &lt;supplier&gt;Fashion Trends&lt;/supplier&gt; 
   &lt;quantity&gt;50&lt;/quantity&gt;
&lt;/order&gt;</eg>
		<p>From this data set, a user might wish to find all the distinct combinations of
				<code>product</code>, <code>size</code>, and <code>color</code> that occur together
			in an <code>order</code>. The following query returns this list, enclosing each distinct
			combination in a new element named <code>option</code>:</p>
		<eg role="parse-test">for $p in fn:distinct-values(/orders/order/product), 
    $s in fn:distinct-values(/orders/order/size), 
    $c in fn:distinct-values(/orders/order/color)
order by $p, $s, $c 
return 
   if (fn:exists(/orders/order[product eq $p 
         and size eq $s and color eq $c])) then 
      &lt;option&gt; 
         &lt;product&gt;{$p}&lt;/product&gt;
         &lt;size&gt;{$s}&lt;/size&gt; 
         &lt;color&gt;{$c}&lt;/color&gt; 
      &lt;/option&gt; 
   else ()</eg>
	</div2>
</inform-div1>
