<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 role="xpath" id="id-backwards-compatibility">
    <head>Incompatibilities relative to XPath 1.0</head>
    
    <p>This appendix provides a summary of the areas of incompatibility between <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> and
            <bibref ref="xpath"/>. In each of these cases, an  <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> processor is compatible with an XPath 2.0 processor <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">or an XPath 3.0 processor</phrase>.</p>

    <p>Three separate cases are considered:</p>

    <olist>
        <item>
            <p>Incompatibilities that exist when source documents have no schema, and when running
                with XPath 1.0 compatibility mode set to true. This specification has been designed
                to reduce the number of incompatibilities in this situation to an absolute minimum,
                but some differences remain and are listed individually.</p>
        </item>

        <item>
            <p>Incompatibilities that arise when XPath 1.0 compatibility mode is set to false. In
                this case, the number of expressions where compatibility is lost is rather
                greater.</p>
        </item>

        <item>
            <p>Incompatibilities that arise when the source document is processed using a schema
                (whether or not XPath 1.0 compatibility mode is set to true). Processing the
                document with a schema changes the way that the values of nodes are interpreted, and
                this can cause an XPath expression to return different results.</p>
        </item>
    </olist>

    <div3 id="id-incompat-in-true-mode">
        <head>Incompatibilities when Compatibility Mode is true</head>

        <p>The list below contains all known areas, within the scope of this specification, where an
            <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> processor running with compatibility mode set to true will produce different
            results from an XPath 1.0 processor evaluating the same expression, assuming that the
            expression was valid in XPath 1.0, and that the nodes in the source document have no
            type annotations other than <code>xs:untyped</code> and
            <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>.</p>

        <p>Incompatibilities in the behavior of individual functions are not listed here, but are
            included in an appendix of <bibref ref="xpath-functions-31"/>.</p>

        <p>Since both XPath 1.0 and <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> leave some aspects of the specification
            implementation-defined, there may be incompatibilities in the behavior of a particular
            implementation that are outside the scope of this specification. Equally, some aspects
            of the behavior of XPath are defined by the host language.</p>


        <olist>
            <item>
                <p>Consecutive comparison operators such as <code>A &lt; B &lt; C</code> were
                    supported in XPath 1.0, but are not permitted by the <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> grammar. In most
                    cases such comparisons in XPath 1.0 did not have the intuitive meaning, so it is
                    unlikely that they have been widely used in practice. If such a construct is
                    found, an <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> processor will report a syntax error, and the construct can
                    be rewritten as <code role="parse-test">(A &lt; B) &lt; C</code></p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>When converting strings to numbers (either explicitly when using the
                        <code>number</code> function, or implicitly say on a function call), certain
                    strings that converted to the special value <code>NaN</code> under XPath 1.0
                    will convert to values other than <code>NaN</code> under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>. These
                    include any number written with a leading <code>+</code> sign, any number in
                    exponential floating point notation (for example <code>1.0e+9</code>), and the
                    strings <code>INF</code> and <code>-INF</code>.</p>

                <p>Furthermore, the strings <code>Infinity</code> and <code>-Infinity</code>, which
                    were accepted by XPath 1.0 as representations of the floating-point values
                    positive and negative infinity, are no longer recognized. They are converted to
                        <code>NaN</code> when running under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> with compatibility mode set to
                    true, and cause a dynamic error when compatibility mode is set to false.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p><phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> does not allow a token starting with a letter to follow immediately
                    after a numeric literal, without intervening whitespace. For example,
                        <code>10div 3</code> was permitted in XPath 1.0, but in <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> must be
                    written as <code>10 div 3</code>.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>The namespace axis is deprecated as of XPath 2.0. Implementations may support the
                    namespace axis for backward compatibility with XPath 1.0, but they are not
                    required to do so. (XSLT 2.0 requires that if XPath backwards compatibility mode
                    is supported, then the namespace axis must also be supported; but other host
                    languages may define the conformance rules differently.)</p>
            </item>


            <item>
                <p>In XPath 1.0, the expression <code>-x|y</code> parsed as <code>-(x|y)</code>, and
                    returned the negation of the numeric value of the first node in the union of
                        <code>x</code> and <code>y</code>. In <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, this expression parses as
                        <code>(-x)|y</code>. When XPath 1.0 Compatibility Mode is true, this will
                    always cause a type error.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>The rules for converting numbers to strings have changed. These may affect the
                    way numbers are displayed in the output of a stylesheet. For numbers whose
                    absolute value is in the range <code>1E-6</code> to <code>1E+6</code>, the
                    result should be the same, but outside this range, scientific format is used for
                    non-integral <code>xs:float</code> and <code>xs:double</code> values.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>If one operand in a general comparison is a single atomic value of type
                        <code>xs:boolean</code>, the other operand is converted to
                        <code>xs:boolean</code> when XPath 1.0 compatibility mode is set to true. In
                    XPath 1.0, if neither operand of a comparison operation using the &lt;, &lt;=,
                    &gt; or &gt;= operator was a node set, both operands were converted to numbers.
                    The result of the expression <code>true() &gt; number('0.5')</code> is therefore
                    true in XPath 1.0, but is false in <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> even when compatibility mode is set
                    to true.</p>
            </item>


            <item>
                <p>In <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, a type error is raised if the PITarget specified in a SequenceType
                    of form <code>processing-instruction(PITarget)</code> is not a valid NCName. In
                    XPath 1.0, this condition was not treated as an error.</p>
            </item>
        </olist>



    </div3>

    <div3 id="id-incompat-in-false-mode">
        <head>Incompatibilities when Compatibility Mode is false</head>

        <p>Even when the setting of the XPath 1.0 compatibility mode is false, many XPath
            expressions will still produce the same results under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> as under XPath 1.0. The
            exceptions are described in this section.</p>

        <p>In all cases it is assumed that the expression in question was valid under XPath 1.0,
            that XPath 1.0 compatibility mode is false, and that all elements and attributes are
            annotated with the types <code>xs:untyped</code> and <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>
            respectively.</p>

        <p>In the description below, the terms <emph>node-set</emph> and <emph>number</emph> are
            used with their XPath 1.0 meanings, that is, to describe expressions which according to
            the rules of XPath 1.0 would have generated a node-set or a number respectively.</p>

        <olist>

            <item>
                <p>When a node-set containing more than one node is supplied as an argument to a
                    function or operator that expects a single node or value, the XPath 1.0 rule was
                    that all nodes after the first were discarded. Under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, a type error
                    occurs if there is more than one node. The XPath 1.0 behavior can always be
                    restored by using the predicate <code>[1]</code> to explicitly select the first
                    node in the node-set.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>In XPath 1.0, the <code>&lt;</code> and <code>&gt;</code> operators, when applied
                    to two strings, attempted to convert both the strings to numbers and then made a
                    numeric comparison between the results. In <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, these operators perform a
                    string comparison using the default collating sequence. (If either value is
                    numeric, however, the results are compatible with XPath 1.0)</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>When an empty node-set is supplied as an argument to a function or operator that
                    expects a number, the value is no longer converted implicitly to NaN. The XPath
                    1.0 behavior can always be restored by using the <code>number</code> function to
                    perform an explicit conversion.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>More generally, the supplied arguments to a function or operator are no longer
                    implicitly converted to the required type, except in the case where the supplied
                    argument is of type <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code> (which will commonly be the
                    case when a node in a schemaless document is supplied as the argument). For
                    example, the function call <code role="parse-test">substring-before(10 div 3,
                        ".")</code> raises a type error under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, because the arguments to
                    the <code>substring-before</code> function must be strings rather than numbers.
                    The XPath 1.0 behavior can be restored by performing an explicit conversion to
                    the required type using a constructor function or cast.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>The rules for comparing a node-set to a boolean have changed. In XPath 1.0, an
                    expression such as <code role="parse-test">$node-set = true()</code> was
                    evaluated by converting the node-set to a boolean and then performing a boolean
                    comparison: so this expression would return <code>true</code> if
                        <code>$node-set</code> was non-empty. In <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, this expression is
                    handled in the same way as other comparisons between a sequence and a singleton:
                    it is <code>true</code> if <code>$node-set</code> contains at least one node
                    whose value, after atomization and conversion to a boolean using the casting
                    rules, is <code>true</code>.</p>

                <p>This means that if <code>$node-set</code> is empty, the result under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>
                    will be <code>false</code> regardless of the value of the boolean operand, and
                    regardless of which operator is used. If <code>$node-set</code> is non-empty,
                    then in most cases the comparison with a boolean is likely to fail, giving a
                    dynamic error. But if a node has the value "0", "1", "true", or "false",
                    evaluation of the expression may succeed.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>Comparisons of a number to a boolean, a number to a string, or a string to a
                    boolean are not allowed in <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>: they result in a type error. In XPath 1.0
                    such comparisons were allowed, and were handled by converting one of the
                    operands to the type of the other. So for example in XPath 1.0 <code
                        role="parse-test">4 = true()</code> was true; <code role="parse-test">4 =
                        "+4"</code> was false (because the string <code>+4</code> converts to
                        <code>NaN</code>), and <code>false = "false"</code> was false (because the
                    string <code>"false"</code> converts to the boolean <code>true</code>). In XPath
                    3.0 all these comparisons are type errors.</p>
            </item>


            <item>
                <p>Additional numeric types have been introduced, with the effect that arithmetic
                    may now be done as an integer, decimal, or single- or double-precision floating
                    point calculation where previously it was always performed as double-precision
                    floating point. The result of the <code>div</code> operator when dividing two
                    integers is now a value of type decimal rather than double. The expression <code
                        role="parse-test">10 div 0</code> raises an error rather than returning
                    positive infinity.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>The rules for converting strings to numbers have changed. The implicit conversion
                    that occurs when passing an <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code> value as an argument
                    to a function that expects a number no longer converts unrecognized strings to
                    the value <code>NaN</code>; instead, it reports a dynamic error. This is in
                    addition to the differences that apply when backwards compatibility mode is set
                    to true.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>Many operations in <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> produce an empty sequence as their result when one
                    of the arguments or operands is an empty sequence. Where the operation expects a
                    string, an empty sequence is usually considered equivalent to a zero-length
                    string, which is compatible with the XPath 1.0 behavior. Where the operation
                    expects a number, however, the result is not the same. For example, if
                        <code>@width</code> returns an empty sequence, then in XPath 1.0 the result
                    of <code role="parse-test">@width+1</code> was <code>NaN</code>, while with
                    <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> it is <code>()</code>. This has the effect that a filter expression
                    such as <code role="parse-test">item[@width+1 != 2]</code> will select items
                    having no <code>width</code> attribute under XPath 1.0, and will not select them
                    under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>The typed value of a comment node, processing instruction node, or namespace node
                    under <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> is of type <code>xs:string</code>, not
                        <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>. This means that no implicit conversions are
                    applied if the value is used in a context where a number is expected. If a
                    processing-instruction node is used as an operand of an arithmetic operator, for
                    example, XPath 1.0 would attempt to convert the string value of the node to a
                    number (and deliver <code>NaN</code> if unsuccessful), while <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> will
                    report a type error.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>In XPath 1.0, it was defined that with an expression of the form <code>A and
                        B</code>, B would not be evaluated if A was false. Similarly in the case of
                        <code>A or B</code>, B would not be evaluated if A was true. This is no
                    longer guaranteed with <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>: the implementation is free to evaluate the two
                    operands in either order or in parallel. This change has been made to give more
                    scope for optimization in situations where XPath expressions are evaluated
                    against large data collections supported by indexes. Implementations may choose
                    to retain backwards compatibility in this area, but they are not obliged to do
                    so.</p>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p>In XPath 1.0, the expression <code>-x|y</code> parsed as <code>-(x|y)</code>, and
                    returned the negation of the numeric value of the first node in the union of
                        <code>x</code> and <code>y</code>. In <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, this expression parses as
                        <code>(-x)|y</code>. When XPath 1.0 Compatibility Mode is false, this will
                    cause a type error, except in the situation where <code>x</code> evaluates to an
                    empty sequence. In that situation, <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> will return the value of
                        <code>y</code>, whereas XPath 1.0 returned the negation of the numeric value
                    of <code>y</code>.</p>
            </item>

        </olist>



    </div3>

    <div3 id="id-incompat-when-using-schema">
        <head>Incompatibilities when using a Schema</head>

        <p>An XPath expression applied to a document that has been processed against a schema will
            not always give the same results as the same expression applied to the same document in
            the absence of a schema. Since schema processing had no effect on the result of an XPath
            1.0 expression, this may give rise to further incompatibilities. This section gives a
            few examples of the differences that can arise.</p>

        <p>Suppose that the context node is an element node derived from the following markup:
                <code>&lt;background color="red green blue"/&gt;</code>. In XPath 1.0, the predicate
                <code>[@color="blue"]</code> would return <code>false</code>. In <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, if the
                <code>color</code> attribute is defined in a schema to be of type
                <code>xs:NMTOKENS</code>, the same predicate will return <code>true</code>.</p>

        <p>Similarly, consider the expression <code role="parse-test">@birth &lt; @death</code>
            applied to the element <code>&lt;person birth="1901-06-06"
                death="1991-05-09"/&gt;</code>. With XPath 1.0, this expression would return false,
            because both attributes are converted to numbers, which returns <code>NaN</code> in each
            case. With <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase>, in the presence of a schema that annotates these attributes as
            dates, the expression returns <code>true</code>.</p>

        <p>Once schema validation is applied, elements and attributes cannot be used as operands and
            arguments of expressions that expect a different data type. For example, it is no longer
            possible to apply the <code>substring</code> function to a date to extract the year
            component, or to a number to extract the integer part. Similarly, if an attribute is
            annotated as a boolean then it is not possible to compare it with the strings
                <code>"true"</code> or <code>"false"</code>. All such operations lead to type
            errors. The remedy when such errors occur is to introduce an explicit conversion, or to
            do the computation in a different way. For example, <code role="parse-test"
                >substring-after(@temperature, "-")</code> might be rewritten as <code
                role="parse-test">abs(@temperature)</code>.</p>

        <p>In the case of an <phrase diff="chg" at="bug28782">XPath 3.1</phrase> implementation that provides the static typing feature, many
            further type errors will be reported in respect of expressions that worked under XPath
            1.0. For example, an expression such as <code role="parse-test">round(../@price)</code>
            might lead to a static type error because the processor cannot infer statically that
                <code role="parse-test">../@price</code> is guaranteed to be numeric.</p>

        <p>Schema validation will in many cases perform whitespace normalization on the contents of
            elements (depending on their type). This will change the result of operations such as
            the <code>string-length</code> function.</p>

        <p>Schema validation augments the data model by adding default values for omitted attributes
            and empty elements.</p>

    </div3>

</div2>
