<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<div1 id="id-introduction">

	<head>Introduction</head> 

	<p role="xquery">As increasing amounts of information are
	stored, exchanged, and presented using XML, the ability to
	intelligently query XML data sources becomes increasingly
	important. One of the great strengths of XML is its
	flexibility in representing many different kinds of
	information from diverse sources. To exploit this flexibility,
	an XML query language must provide features for retrieving and
	interpreting information from these diverse sources.</p> 

	<p role="xquery">XQuery is designed to meet the requirements
	identified by the W3C XML Query Working Group <bibref ref="xquery-11-requirements"/>
  and the use cases in <bibref ref="UseCases"/>. 
  It is designed to be a language in which queries are concise and easily
	understood. It is also flexible enough to query a broad
	spectrum of XML information sources, including both databases
	and documents. The Query Working Group has identified a
	requirement for both a non-XML query syntax and an
	XML-based query syntax. XQuery is designed to meet the first
	of these requirements.  XQuery is derived from an XML query
	language called Quilt <bibref ref="Quilt"/>, which in turn
	borrowed features from several other languages, including
	XPath 1.0 <bibref ref="xpath"/>, XQL <bibref ref="XQL"/>,
	XML-QL <bibref ref="XML-QL"/>, SQL <bibref ref="SQL"/>, and
	OQL <bibref ref="ODMG"/>. </p>

	<p role="xpath">The primary purpose of XPath is to address the
	nodes of <bibref ref="XML"/> or <bibref ref="XML1.1"/> trees.

	XPath gets its name from its use of a path notation for navigating through the hierarchical structure of an XML
	document.

        XPath uses a compact, non-XML syntax to facilitate use of
        XPath within URIs and XML attribute values.</p>

<p><termdef id="dt-datamodel" term="data model">&language; operates on the abstract,
	logical structure of an XML document, rather than its surface
	syntax.  This logical structure, known as the <term>data
	model</term>,  is defined in <bibref ref="xpath-datamodel-11"/>.</termdef></p>

	<p role="xpath">XPath is designed to be embedded in a
	<term>host language</term> such as <bibref ref="xslt-21"/> or
	<bibref ref="xquery-11"/>. XPath has a natural subset that can be
	used for matching (testing whether or not a node matches a
	pattern); this use of XPath is described in <bibref ref="xslt-21"/>.</p>

	<p>XQuery Version 1.1 is an extension of XPath Version
	2.1. 

	In general, any expression that is syntactically valid and executes
	successfully in both XPath 2.1 and XQuery 1.1 will return the
	same result in both languages. There are a few exceptions to this
	rule:

	<ulist>
	<item><p>Because XQuery expands 
<phrase role="xquery">
 <termref def="dt-predefined-entity-reference">predefined entity references</termref> and <termref def="dt-character-reference">character references</termref>
</phrase>
<phrase role="xpath">
predefined entity references and character references
</phrase>
 and XPath does not, expressions containing these produce different results in the two languages. For instance, the value of the string literal <code role="parse-test">"&amp;amp;"</code> is <code>&amp;</code> in XQuery, and <code>&amp;amp;</code> in XPath. (XPath is often embedded in other languages, which may expand predefined entity references or character references before the XPath expression is evaluated.)</p></item>
	<item><p>If XPath 1.0 compatibility mode is enabled, XPath behaves differently from XQuery in a number of ways, 
<phrase role="xpath">which are noted throughout this document, and listed in <specref ref="id-incompat-in-false-mode"/>.</phrase>
<phrase role="xquery">which are discussed in <bibref ref="xpath-21"/>.</phrase></p></item>
	</ulist></p>

	<p>Because these languages are so closely related, their grammars
	and language descriptions are generated from a common source
	to ensure consistency, and the editors of these specifications
	work together closely.</p>

	<p>&language; also depends on and is closely related to the
	following specifications:</p>

	<ulist>
	  <item>
            <p><bibref ref="xpath-datamodel-11"/> defines the data model that underlies all &language; expressions.</p>
	  </item>

          <item>
	  <p>The type system of &language; is based on <bibref ref="XMLSchema"/>.</p>
	  </item>

	  <item>
	  <p>The built-in function library  and the operators supported by
	  &language; are defined in <bibref ref="xpath-functions-11"/>.</p>
	  </item>

	  <item role="xquery">
	  <p>One requirement in <bibref ref="xquery-11-requirements"/> is that
	  an XML query language have both a human-readable syntax and
	  an XML-based syntax.  The XML-based syntax for XQuery is
	  described in <bibref ref="xqueryx-11"/>. </p> 
          </item>

        </ulist>

<p><termdef id="dt-xquery-11-processor" term="XQuery 1.1 Processor">An
<term>XQuery 1.1 Processor</term> processes a query according to the
XQuery 1.1 specification.</termdef></p>
<p><termdef id="dt-xquery-10-processor" term="XQuery 1.0 Processor">An
<term>XQuery 1.0 Processor</term> processes a query according to the
XQuery 1.0 specification.</termdef></p>

	
	<p>This document specifies a grammar for &language;, using the
		same basic EBNF notation used in <bibref ref="XML"/>. 
    Unless otherwise noted (see <specref ref="lexical-structure"/>), 
    whitespace is not significant in <phrase role="xquery">queries</phrase><phrase role="xpath">expressions</phrase>. 
    Grammar productions are introduced together with the features that they describe,
    and a complete grammar is also presented in the appendix [<specref ref="nt-bnf"/>]. 
    The appendix is the normative version.</p><p>In the grammar productions in this document,
    named symbols are underlined and literal text is enclosed in double quotes. 
    For example, the following  production describes the syntax of a function call:</p><scrap> 
		  <head></head> 
		  <prodrecap ref="FunctionCall" id="fakeid"/> 
		</scrap><p>The production should be read as follows: A
		function call consists of an <nt
		def="EQName">EQName</nt> followed by an
		open-parenthesis. The open-parenthesis is followed by
		an optional argument list. The argument list (if
		present) consists of one or more expressions,
		separated by commas. The optional argument list is
		followed by a close-parenthesis. </p>


<p>This document normatively defines the static and dynamic semantics of
&language;. In this document, examples and material labeled as "Note"
are provided for explanatory purposes and are not normative.</p>


		<p>Certain aspects of language
		processing are described in this specification as
		<term>implementation-defined</term> or
		<term>implementation-dependent</term>.</p>

<ulist>
  <item>
    <p><termdef id="dt-implementation-defined" term="implementation defined"><term>Implementation-defined</term>
		indicates an aspect that may differ between
		implementations, but must be specified by the
		implementor for each particular
		implementation.</termdef></p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>
      <termdef id="dt-implementation-dependent" term="implementation
		dependent"><term>Implementation-dependent</term>
		indicates an aspect that may differ between
		implementations, is not specified by this or any W3C
		specification, and is not required to be specified by
		the implementor for any particular
		implementation.</termdef></p>
  </item>
</ulist>

<p role="xpath">A language aspect described in this specification as
<term>implementation-defined</term> or <term>implementation
dependent</term> may be further constrained by the specifications of a
host language in which XPath is embedded.</p>


</div1>
