<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><div1 role="xqueryx" id="xqueryx-id-mime-type">  <head>The <code>application/xquery+xml</code> Media Type</head>  <p>This Appendix specifies the media type for XQueryX Version 1.0.  XQueryX is     the XML syntax of a language, XQuery, for querying over     data from XML data sources, as specified in <bibref ref="xquery-11"/>.</p>  <note><p>Specification of media types is described in           <bibref ref="RFC3023"/>.</p></note>  <div2 id="xqueryx-mime-introduction">    <head>Introduction</head>    <p>This document, together with its normative references, defines the       XML syntax for the XML Query language XQuery Version 1.0.        This Appendix specifies the <code>application/xquery+xml</code> media type,       which is intended to be used for transmitting queries expressed in the       XQueryX syntax.</p><!-- Changed "document" to "media type" per Liam Quin -->	  <p>This media type is being submitted to the IESG for       review, approval, and registration with IANA. </p>    <p>This document was prepared by members of the W3C XML Query Working       Group.  Please send comments to public-qt-comments@w3.org,       a public mailing list with archives at       <loc href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-qt-comments">http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-qt-comments</loc>. </p>  </div2>  <div2 id="xqueryx-mime-registration">    <head>Registration of MIME Media Type <code>application/xquery+xml</code></head>    <p>MIME media type name:  <code>application</code></p>    <p>MIME subtype name:    <code>xquery+xml</code></p>    <p>Required parameters:  none</p>    <p>Optional parameters: <code>charset</code></p>    <p>This parameter has identical semantics to the       <code>charset</code> parameter of the <code>application/xml</code>       media type as specified in [RFC 3023].</p>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-encoding">      <head>Encoding Considerations</head>      <p>By virtue of XSLT content being XML, it has the same considerations      when sent as "<code>application/xquery+xml</code>" as does XML.       See [RFC 3023], section 3.2.</p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-security">      <head>Security Considerations</head>        <p>Queries written in XQuery may cause arbitrary URIs or IRIs to be dereferenced.            Therefore, the security issues of [RFC3987] Section 8 should be considered.            In addition, the contents of resources identified by <code>file:</code> URIs can in           some cases be accessed, processed and returned as results.            XQuery expressions can invoke any of the functions defined in           XQuery 1.0 and XPath 2.0 Functions and Operators, including <code>file-exists()</code>;           a <code>doc()</code> function also allows local filesystem probes as well as           access to any URI-defined resource accessible from the system           evaluating the XQuery expression. </p>        <p>XQuery is a full declarative programming language, and supports           user-defined functions, external function libraries (modules)           referenced by URI, and system-specific "native" functions. </p>        <p>Arbitrary recursion is possible, as is arbitrarily large           memory usage, and implementations may place limits on CPU and           memory usage, as well as restricting access to system-defined functions. </p>        <p>The XML Query Working group is working on a facility to allow XQuery           expressions to be used to create and update persistent data.            Untrusted queries should not be given write access to data. </p>        <p>Furthermore, because the XQuery language permits extensions, it is           possible that application/xquery may describe content that has security           implications beyond those described here. </p>    </div3>     <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-interoperability">      <head>Interoperability Considerations</head>	    <p>See <xspecref spec="XQ" ref="id-xquery-conformance"/>. </p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-pubspec">      <head>Published specification</head>      <p>This media type registration is for XQueryX documents as described         by the XQueryX 1.0 specification, which is located at         <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xqueryx/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xqueryx/</loc>.          It is also appropriate to use this media type with later versions of         the XQueryX language. </p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-applications">      <head>Applications That Use This Media Type</head>    	<p>The public <loc href="http://www.w3.org/XML/Query">XQuery Web page</loc>         lists more than two dozen implementations of the XQuery language,	       both proprietary and open source.  Some of these are known to         support XQueryX. </p>  	  <p>This new media type is being registered to allow for deployment	       of XQueryX on the World Wide Web.</p>      <p>There is no experimental, vendor specific, or personal tree         predecessor to "application/xquery+xml", reflecting the fact         that no applications currently recognize it. This new type is         being registered in order to allow for the expected deployment         of XQueryX 1.0 on the World Wide Web, as a first class XML application. </p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-additional">      <head>Additional Information</head>      <div4 id="xqueryx-mime-recognizing">        <head>Recognizing XQuery Files ("Magic Numbers")</head>        <p>Although no byte sequences can be counted on to consistently           identify XQueryX, XQueryX documents will have the sequence           "http://www.w3.org/2005/XQueryX" to identify the XQueryX           namespace.            This sequence will normally be found in a namespace attribute           of the first element in the document. </p>      </div4>      <div4 id="xqueryx-mime-extensions">        <head>File Extensions</head>      	<p>The most common file extension in use for XQueryX is	      <code>.xqx</code>. </p>      </div4>      <div4 id="xqueryx-mime-macfiletype">        <head>Macintosh File Type Code(s)</head>      	<p>The appropriate Macintosh file type code is <code>TEXT</code>.</p>      </div4>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-author">      <head>Person and Email Address to Contact For Further Information</head>      <p>Jim Melton, Oracle Corp.,          <loc href="mailto:jim.melton@oracle.com">jim.melton@oracle.com</loc></p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-intended-usage">      <head>Intended Usage</head>      <p>COMMON</p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-restrictions">      <head>Restrictions on usage</head>      <p>The intended usage of this media type is for interchange         of XQueryX expressions.</p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-owner">      <head>Author/Change Controller</head>      <p>XQuery was produced by, and is maintained by, the World Wide Web         Consortium's XML Query Working Group.  The W3C has change         control over this specification. </p>    </div3>    <div3 id="xqueryx-mime-fragments">      <head>Fragment Identifiers</head>      <p>For documents labeled as "<code>application/xquery+xml</code>",         the fragment identifier notation is exactly that for         "<code>application/xml</code>", as specified in [RFC 3023]. </p>    </div3>  </div2></div1>